Finding Aid for Merriam Family Papers, 1914-1964
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Merriam Family Papers 1914-1964
Merriam family.
86977 Aa/2; AC; UAl
The papers of the Merriam family of Grand Rapids and Holland, Michigan, reflect chiefly the business activities and leisure time interests of Warren Sturtevant Merriam, plant manager of Baker Furniture, Inc. of Holland and member of the Macatawa Bay Yacht Club. There is also some material concerning his father, the Reverend Charles Wolcott Merriam, his mother, Julia Sturtevant Merriam, and his wife, Helen Bell Merriam.
2 linear feet
3 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Merriam family papers were the gift of Stanton W. Todd (donor no. 5611 ) and came to the library in May 1985.
The collection is open to research.
The Reverend Charles W. Merriam was born in 1876 in Rochester, N.Y. He received a B.S. degree from Amherst College, attended the Hartford Theological Seminary, received his B.D. degree at Yale in 1901, and his D.D. degree from Olivet College. Reverend Merriam served as pastor to the Second Congregational Church in Cohasset, Massachusetts (1901-1904), the Second Congregational Church in Greenfield, Massachusetts (1904-1916), the Park (First) Congregational Church in Grand Rapids, Michigan (1916-1933) and the United Church of Old Deerfield, Massachusetts (1933-1939). He married Julia Bemis Sturtevant in 1900. The couple had three children: Warren Sturtevant, Charles Wolcott, Jr., and Julia Elizabeth. Following his retirement in 1939, the Merriam's moved to Claremont, California. Julia died in 1941; in 1942 Charles married Mrs. Olive S. Whitfield, who was killed in an automobile accident in 1951. Charles died in 1956 at Pilgrim's Place, a rest home for retired congregational ministers.
Warren Sturtevant Merriam, called Bill, was the elder son of Charles and Julia. He was born in 1901, in Cohasset, Massachusetts. Warren was student at Colgate University from 1919-1920, and a graduate of the University of Michigan in 1923. He worked for the Berkey and Gay Furniture Company of Grand Rapids from 1922-1930, and for Manufacturers Selling Agency in Los Angeles from 1930-1934, before coming to Baker Furniture, Inc. of Holland, Michigan. At Baker, he served as plant manager. In 1925 he married Helen Victoria Bell of Chicago. She was a graduate of Wellesley who did graduate work at the University of Chicago and taught school in Chicago before her marriage. Warren and Helen were active members of the Macatawa Bay Yacht Club, for which Warren served as Commodore in 1949. Both were involved members of the Grace Episcopal Church of Holland, and Helen especially was active in Episcopal Church affairs in Western Michigan. Warren died in 1972, and Helen in 1984.
The papers have been divided into nine series: Baker Furniture, Inc., Macatawa Bay Yacht Club, Warren Sturtevant Merriam, Helen Bell Merriam, Charles Wolcott Merriam, Julia Sturtevant Merriam, Park Congregational Church, Grace Episcopal Church, and Photographs and Slides.
Subjects:
Baker Furniture Company.; Clergy--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Women--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Women--Michigan--Holland.; Congregational churches--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Holland.; Furniture industry and trade--Michigan--Holland.; Grace Episcopal Church (Holland, Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Holland (Mich.); Furniture workers--Labor unions--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Merriam, Helen Bell, d. 1984.; Merriam, Julia Bemis Sturtevant, 1874-1941.; Merriam, Warren Sturtevant, 1901-1972.; Merriam family.; Park Congregational Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Yachting.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Baker Furniture Company.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Holland.; Churches--Michigan--Holland.; Furniture industry--Michigan--Holland.; Grace Episcopal Church (Holland, Mich.); Holland (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Holland (Mich.)--Churches.; Holland (Mich.)--Furniture industry.; Merriam family.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Baker Furniture, Inc.
  The Baker Furniture, Inc. series contains interesting material dating chiefly from the 1940's and 1950's. This includes a notebook containing internal production reports, memos written by Merriam to the foremen of various departments and speeches given by Merriam to foremen and crew leaders. These materials reflect a concern with productivity and, increasingly, with labor costs. Especially interesting is a folder of letters and flyers representing both management and labor viewpoints during an unsuccessful 1953 CIO union drive.
  - Memoranda and International Production Reports 1935-1959, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - "The Baker Bugle and Market Journal," 1949-1957 (Box 1)
  - CIO Union Drive July 1953 (Box 1)
    (includes union and management leaflets and letters)
  - Promotional Literature and Clippings 1939-1960 (Box 1)
- Macatawa Bay Yacht Club
  The Macatawa Bay Yacht Club series reflects chiefly Merriam's appointment as Commodore in 1949. Included are the club's by-laws, and minutes and correspondence.
  - By-Laws 1951 (Box 1)
  - Minutes and Calendar of events 1949 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1949 (Box 1)
  - Loose scrapbook items 1940-1964 (Box 1)
- Warren Sturtevant Merriam (1901-1972)
  The Warren Sturtevant Merriam series consists of logs and diaries from three cruises on the Yacht Bel Mer taken by the Merriam's and their friends in 1952, 1953 and 1956. These are humorous, through difficult to follow due to heavy use of nicknames and sailing jargon.
  - Logs and diaries from yacht Bel Mer 1952-1953, 1956 (Box 1)
- Helen Bell Merriam (d. 1984)
  Helen Bell Merriam was apparently a daughter of a wealthy Chicago family. The photograph album in her series dates from 1914-1947 and provides an interesting picture of the vacation activities enjoyed by a young woman of her class. Other materials include a brief correspondence with a distant relative concerning the genealogy of the Merriam family, and a biographical sketch.
  - Photograph album 1914-1917 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (includes letters, genealogical chart, biographical sketch) (Box 1)
- Charles Wolcott Merriam (1876-1956)
  The Charles Wolcott Merriam series contains one printed sermon delivered by the Reverend Merriam in 1948 at the Park Congregational Church. There are also obituary clippings and typed letters containing his plans for his own memorial service and a list of bequests.
  - The Search for the Unseen (printed sermon) 1948 (Box 1)
  - Funeral plans and list of bequests 1954 (Box 1)
  - Clippings and obituaries (Box 1)
- Julia Sturtevant Merriam (1874-1941)
  The Julia Sturtevant Merriam series consists of a privately printed memorial volume, What Is Faith?, put together by her family and friends upon her death in 1941.
  - What is Faith? (Memorial volume) 1941 (Box 1)
- Park Congregational Church, Grand Rapids
  The Park Congregational Church series consists of church bulletins and clippings documenting the involvement of the Merriam's in various church activities.
  - Bulletins, Clippings, etc. (Box 1)
- Grace Episcopal Church, Holland
  The Grace Episcopal Church series consists of church bulletins and clippings documenting the involvement of the Merriam's in various church activities.
  - Bulletins, Clippings, etc. (Box 1)
- Photographs and Slides
  Photographs and Slides contain family pictures as well as pictures from Baker Furniture, Inc. and the Park Congregational Church and the Grace Episcopal Church. A set of slides from the convention of the Episcopal Church in 1960 in Detroit has with it a typed inventory of the numbered slides.
  - Family portraits (Box 1)
  - Baker Furniture (Box 1)
    (see also 1 outsize item, UAl)
  - Church (Box 1)
  - Slides from convention of Episcopal Church, Detroit 1960 (Box 1)
  - Unprocessed photos, slides, etc. (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  - Helen Bell scrapbook re. Wellesley College life, ca. 1917-ca. 1921 (Volume 1)
  - Warren S. Merriam scrapbook re: Colgate student life, ca. 1919-ca. 1922 (Volume 2)
  - Helen Bell Merriam and Warren S. Merriam scrapbook 1921-1948 (Volume 3)
  - Warren S. Merriam scrapbooks (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Personal memorabilia (Box 2)
    (unprocessed)